Only one will claim the night
Batman is a fantasy, action, crime film directed by Tim Burton.
Having witnessed his parents' brutal murder as a child, millionaire philanthropist Bruce Wayne fights crime in
Gotham City disguised as Batman, a costumed hero who strikes fear into the hearts of villains.
But when a deformed madman known as 'The Joker' seizes control of Gotham's criminal underworld, Batman must face his
most ruthless nemesis ever while protecting both his identity and his love interest, reporter Vicki Vale.
Bruce Wayne / Batman, played by Michael Keaton.
Jack Napier / The Joker, played by Jack Nicholson.
Vicki Vale, played by Kim Basinger.
Alexander Knox, played by Robert Wuhl.
Commissioner James Gordon, played by Pat Hingle.
Harvey Dent, played by Billy Dee Williams.
Batman is a 1989 superhero film based on the DC Comics
character, created by Bob Kane and Bill Finger.
Directed by Tim Burton, it is the first installment of
Warner Bros.' initial Batman film series.
The film stars Jack Nicholson, Michael Keaton, Kim Basinger, Robert Wuhl, Pat
Hingle, Billy Dee Williams, Michael Gough, and Jack Palance.
The film's score was composed by Danny Elfman, and songs were written by Prince.
The film takes place early in the war on crime of the title character (Keaton)
and depicts his conflict with his archenemy the Joker (Nicholson).
After Burton was hired as director in 1986, Steve Englehart and Julie Hickson
wrote film treatments before Sam Hamm wrote the first screenplay.
Batman was not greenlit until after the success of Burton's Beetlejuice (1988).
The tone and themes of the film were partly influenced by Alan Moore and Brian
Bolland's The Killing Joke and Frank Miller's The Dark Knight Returns.
The film primarily adapts and then diverges from the "Red Hood" origin story for the Joker, having Batman inadvertently cause
gangster Jack Napier to fall into Axis Chemical acid, triggering his transformation into the psychotic Joker.
Additionally, Batman co-creator Bob Kane worked as a consultant for the film.
Numerous leading men were considered for the role
of Batman before Keaton was cast.
Keaton's casting was controversial since, by 1988, he had become typecast as a comedic
actor and many observers had doubt he could portray a serious role.
Nicholson accepted the role of the Joker under strict conditions that dictated top billing, a portion of
the film's earnings (including associated merchandise), and his own shooting schedule.
Filming took place at Pinewood Studios from October 1988 to January 1989.
The budget escalated from $30 million to $48 million, while the 1988
Writers Guild of America strike forced Hamm to drop out.
Warren Skaaren did rewrites, with additional uncredited
drafts done by Charles McKeown and Jonathan Gems.
Batman was both critically and financially successful,
earning over $400 million in box office totals.
Critics and audiences particularly praised Nicholson and Keaton's performances,
Burton's direction, the production design, and composer Danny Elfman's score.
It was the sixth-highest-grossing film in history at the time of its release.
The film received several Saturn Award nominations and a Golden Globe nomination for
Nicholson's performance, and won the Academy Award for Best Art Direction.
The film was followed by three sequels: Batman Returns (1992), with both Burton and Keaton returning; Batman Forever (1995), with Joel
Schumacher directing and Val Kilmer in the lead role; and Batman & Robin (1997), which featured George Clooney in the role.
Keaton would later reprise the role of Batman in the DC
Extended Universe film The Flash (2023).
The film also led to the development of Batman: The Animated Series (1992–1995), which in turn began the DC Animated Universe of
spin-off media, and has influenced Hollywood's modern marketing and development techniques of the superhero film genre.
Two sequel novels were written by John Jackson Miller, Batman:
Resurrection (2024) and Batman: Revolution (2025).
The film explores themes of dual identity, double
life, chemical, crime fighter, superhero.
The tone is dark.